All right. So now let's tackle what exactly is HTML, and how do we use it to structure our web sites.
So no matter what you use as your browser - it could be Chrome,
it could be Safari or Firefox -
they all have a single purpose, and that's to interpret your files such as your HTML files, your CSS files,
your Javascript files, into a web site that should be displayed.
So, for example, we've got a little bit of HTML code here that says that our web site should have a title
called
Hello.
And in the body there should be a heading that says Hello World.
So if we pass that code into our browser it will open it and display it like so, with the title of the
web site usually on the tab bar, and that h1, or that big heading, showing up in the body of our web site.
So, before we dive deep into this, it's really important to remember that HTML is the foundation of
all web sites.
So, for example, you won't see web sites that are created using just a CSS file or just a Javascript file
but you can create web sites using just an HTML file.
Now it might not look great.
It'll probably look like it came from the 90s but it does enable your web site to display text or various
elements such as images or forms or tables depending on how you code up the HTML file.
So, HTML stands for Hypertext Markup Language, and the really important part here is the word
markup because there's many markup languages.
For example you might have heard of things such as XML, Extensible Markup Language, or GML, Generalized
Markup Language, and all of these languages share a common history.
They're based off the markup that used to be put into manuscripts where editors would mark up the manuscript
and either specify changes to the author or specify structure and layout to the publishers.
So for example you might have the squiggly line that shows the publishers that this part should be printed
in bold or this part should be printed in italics, and HTML works in much the same way.
You can specify the layout and structure of your website by using HTML tags.
So if you head over to your browser and go to a web site called codepen.io, then we can have a
look and have a play around with real life HTML. So, you don't have to sign up.
Just head over to codepen.io, and then hit Create, New Pen, and then we're going to change the view
to a format like this.
So this is the live version of our web site and these are the places where we're going to put our code.
So, as you can see, Code Pen let’s you put in HTML, CSS and Javascript, which will together get interpreted
and get shown on the left as your web site.
Now, as we're only working with HTML at the moment, I'm going to minimize the CSS and Javascript sections
and I'm just going to work from the HTML section.
Now we're going to need some text to work with or have something which we can give structure to.
If you head over to gutenberg.org/ebooks/1661, you get taken to The Adventures of Sherlock
Holmes by Arthur Conan Doyle.
So one of my favorite books of all time.
If you have a look down here you can see that you can view the book as plain text
or you can read this book online as HTML.
So this is what the plain text looks like.
It has all of the text in the book but absolutely no structure.
But, when we have a look at the HTML file, you can see that it has laid out the book with a structure
that is more human readable.
And this is what we're going to replicate using HTML.
So if you go ahead and just copy this part -The Adventures of Sherlock Holmes by Sir Arthur Conan Doyle -
and you copy and place it into your pen,
so in the HTML section here. Now you can see that all of this text gets put onto the screen with absolutely
no structure.
And in order for this to start looking like this we're going to start adding a little bit of HTML.
So the first thing we can see is that this is the largest heading on the page. So we can make our website
look like that
also, by adding an h1 tag into our HTML. So the tags start with angular brackets and end with angular brackets
and in the middle is the type of element or the type of tag you want to use.
Now it's really important that when you open tags that you also close them, because as you can see here
I've got an open tag
but I have yet to close it, and it thinks that the entire contents of my page should be made into the
largest heading possible and that's not what I want.
I only want it for this section - The Adventures of Sherlock Holmes.
So, in order to close the tag, it's the same angle brackets,
but then I have to use a forward slash and then write h1.
So now only this part is an h1 or a large heading.
Now if we have a look at the other parts I would say that this word - by - is a little bit smaller than
the author's name.
So let's structure this as a heading also.
But let's make it a subtitle so let's make it a slightly smaller heading and to do that we can simply
wrap this text around an h2 tag. And now we have Sir Arthur Conan Doyle as a heading but in a smaller
size and shown with less importance than the big title.
So now finally we have this word - by -
and I reckon that's one size smaller than this heading, so let's go ahead and wrap this inside an h3.
So I hope you're starting to get the gist.
The heading tags get smaller as the number goes up.
So for example if I changed this to an h4 it gets even smaller, h5 smaller still, and all the way
until h6, which is the smallest font size for the heading element.
Now, if you keep going to h7, you'll notice that it doesn't do anything anymore.
It doesn't change the heading size and that's because the heading elements only go from h1 to h6.
Now how do I know that,
I hear you ask.
So this is a good point in the course to introduce documentation.
And the reason why I'm talking about it so early on is because of how important it is to your journey
as a web developer.
So one of the key skills in becoming a great web developer, or in fact any sort of programmer, is getting
good at finding out how you can help yourself and a lot of that involves getting good at googling.
How do you find the specific piece of information that's going to help you achieve what it is that you
want or help you understand what it is that you want to know.
So in this case we're talking about headings and we are using HTML and I'm going to add in the name of
the documentation that I prefer to use which is MDN and it stands for the Mozilla Developer Network,
so the same people who made Firefox for example.
So if I go ahead and hit enter,
you see a whole bunch of results come up.
And the most relevant for us is the h1 to h6 and it talks about headings.
So if we click on that you can learn more about the heading elements used in HTML and they even have
example code snippets that show you what it would look like rendered in a browser.
Now there's a couple of sources for documentation.
One is of course MDN. Another one is called W3 Schools.
So let's see if we try W3 Schools with HTML
and we're talking about headings, right?
Let’s see what we get here.
So HTML Headings is the first result that comes up.
And similarly you've got the code examples, you've got the results and you've got a little bit of notes
that tell you how you should be using your headings.
So both of these places have a lot of really useful usage notes and it's worth reading through when you’re
first coming across a particular element.
That way you'll have a good foundation of knowledge when you start to build and create your own web sites.
So I want to show you one last resource that I quite like using, which is called
devdocs.io.
And this is basically a web site that puts together a lot of the useful documentation in a structure that
I find to be quite handy.
So if we have a look inside the HTML5 tab, and we go into the elements, we can see that there's a total
of 135 elements and if you scroll down you can see that we've got h1 through to h6.
And if you click on any of these then it brings up actually the MDN documentation so you can see
that it's similar to what we saw on MDN but it's just structured in a very simple way and it's very
easy to follow.
So that's definitely a web site that's worth bookmarking.
So if we head back over to our HTML file we’re going to change that back to an h3, which is an
HTML tag that actually exists as opposed to something like h9.
So the next thing that we need to do in order to better replicate this web site is to add some space
between these lines.
Now in a word processor such as Word or Google Docs you'll be able to simply just hit enter a few times or
hit return a few times and get that spacing show up.
Now unfortunately in HTML it doesn't quite work like that.
It's a little bit more complicated. In order to create that spacing,
we actually have to use an HTML element called a line break and it's written like so.
And the interesting thing about this HTML element is that it doesn't require both an open and a close
tag.
So we have the h1 through to h6 tags.
You can see that we started out by marking the text with an h1 and then we close it off with a closing
tag but the line break element works all by itself and you can even put it inside like so to make this
part go onto a new line.
Now this is a good time point to review the anatomy of HTML tags.