Welcome to the complete web developer boot camp. My name is Angela.
I'm a senior developer and the lead instructor at the App Brewery,
London's highest-rated programming Bootcamp. To date, I taught over 120,000 students - in person and online.
I'm so excited that I now have the privilege of being your instructor for this course. In the coming
lessons
you can look forward to the same curriculum as our in-person programming bootcamp.
So it doesn't matter if you've never programmed before.
because I'm going to start at the beginning and I'll take you step by step so that you understand every
single line of code that we write together. We'll be covering some of the latest tools and technology
including HTML, CSS,  Javascript, MongoDB,  Express JS ... and a whole lot more.
As a student on this course, you're going to be saving yourself a lot of time because instead of having
to deal with outdated or incomprehensible tutorials, you now get access to a fully up-to-date curriculum
which is going to take you from beginner to mastery.
You're also going to be saving yourself a lot of money because instead of having to take time off work
or spend tens of thousands of dollars on an in-person programming bootcamp, you'll get access to exactly
the same content, but you get to do it in your own time and on your own terms for a fraction of the
price.
By the end of the course, you will be fluently programming by yourself and along the way, you will have
built over 16 fully-fledged websites and a web application ready to take on a job as a professional
developer or to build your next tech startup.
One of my greatest passions in life is understanding how humans learn.
I've spent years researching programming education and applying what I found to designing bootcamp curriculums.
I have some of the highest-rated development courses across the web but don't just take my word for
it. Check out my past students had to say.
This is the most comprehensive and most up to date course on full-stack web development.
There are new modules being added constantly to make sure that you are always up to date with the latest
technologies.
As a student on this course
you now have access to everything you need to learn to code and become a web developer.
So what are you still waiting for?
Join me on the next lesson and let's get started.